Register of the Konstantin Vasil'evich Semchevskii Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Konstantin Vasil'evich Semchevskii papers
1917-1978
2001C38
Hoover Institution Archives
2 microfilm reels (0.3 linear feet)
Memoirs, other writings, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the Russian Civil War in Siberia, and to Russian émigré affairs.
Semchevskii, Konstantin Vasil'evich, 1894-1978
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Colonel K. V. Semchevskii was born on 6 May 1894 (O. S.) in Tiflis (Tbilisi). After graduating with honors from the Corps de Pages in 1913, he was commissioned as a sub-lieutenant in the Life Guard Horse Artillery, with which he served until 1917. In October of that year, he entered the General Staff Academy, where he studied through July 1918, when, with a group of fellow officers, he escaped from Ekaterinburg to join Siberian White military units operating in the area. In August 1918 he was appointed head of the operations section of the army staff in Omsk, and promoted to the rank of guards captain the following month. In December 1918, he was appointed an instructor at an army school in Vladivostok. In November 1919, he assumed the duties of chief of staff of the 1st Cavalry Division, taking command of its remnants to lead them out of encirclement in January 1920. The following month, Semchevskii was promoted to the rank of colonel and appointed quartermaster general of the 3rd Army (from March 1920 - III Corps).
Along with his wife, Elena Vasil'evna Semchevskaia (a writer and poet), Semchevskii lived in China until emigrating to the United States in 1950. He wrote his memoirs, primarily of life in the Corps de Pages, and maintained correspondence with many of his fellow pages through the 1970s. He also taught at the Army Language School in Monterey, California, where he died in February 1978.
Chronology
1894 May 6 Born, Russia
1913 Graduated, Corps de Pages, St. Petersburg, Russia Commissioned as a Sub-Lieutenant in the Life-Guard Horse Artillery
1918 Captain, Siberian Army Temporary chief of operations section, Siberian Army headquarters
1919 Instructor, military school, Vladivostok
1920 February Promoted to Colonel and appointed Quartermaster-General, Third Army, Siberia
1950 Arrived, United States
1978 Died, United States
Scope and Content Note
K. V. Semchevskii was a Russian army colonel and member of the association of graduates of the Corps de Pages and former officers of the Guards Horse Artillery. Most of the correspondence (almost entirely with former comrades-in-arms), writings, and subject file reflect his involvement in these organizations and general information on Russian military history. The SUBJECT FILE/Russia. Armiia/General contains the diary of Gen. Bezobrazov for 1917-1924.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Russia. Armiia--Officers; Russia.; Russians--United States.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1917-1978 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings, family file relating to E. V. Semchevskaia (wife), military service records, scrapbook, and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1947-1978 (Box 1-2)
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Writings, 1948-1975 (Box 2)
  Articles, letter to the editor and fragments of memoirs, arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, 1917-1978 (Box 2)
  Clippings, correspondence, lists, writings and a diary, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 2)
  Three prints and a color reproduction of a painting
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1917-1978 (Box 1)
  - Clippings about or mentioning Semchevskii (Folder 1: 1)
  - Family file - Semchevskaia, Elena V. (wife)
    - Clippings about or mentioning Semchevskaia (Folder 1: 2)
    - Identity papers (Folder 1: 3)
    - Letter of thanks (Folder 1: 4)
    - Writings. (Folder 1: 5)
      Include letter to the editor and two short stories
  - Military service records. (Folder 1: 6)
    General note
    See also scrapbook
  - Scrapbook. (Folder 1: 7)
    Includes photographs, military service records, and miscellaneous documents
  - Miscellany. (Folder 1: 8)
    Includes statement and other documents relating to Semchevskii's activities during and after the Second World War
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1947-1978
  - General, 1957-1977 and undated (Folder 1: 9)
  - Unidentified, 1973-1977 and undated (Folder 1: 10)
  - Andro de Lanzheron, Svetlana Romanovna, 1976 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Aprelev, V., 1976-1978 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Armfel'dt, Vladimir, 1976-1978 and undated (Folder 1: 13)
  - Babushkin, Boris Alekseevich, 1976-1977 and undated (Folder 1: 14)
  - Barklai de Tolli, 1958 and undated (Folder 1: 15)
  - Belosel'skii, Sergei, Prince, 1947-1954 and undated (Folder 1: 16)
  - Burman, V., 1976-1977 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Chagin, Gleb, 1978 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Daragan, Ivan and Elena, 1966-1973 and undated (Folder 1: 19)
  - Derozhinskii, B., 1975 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Domershchikov, N., 1970 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Gattenberger, P., 1976 (Folder 1: 22)
    Includes associated correspondence with V. Sokolov, 1976
  - Gershel'man family, 1975-1976 and undated (Folder 1: 23)
  - Gonetskii, Nikolai, undated (Folder 1: 24)
  - Grekova, Liubov' Sergeevna, 1975 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Il'ina, Ol'ga, 1975 (?) (Folder 1: 26)
  - Khitrovo, Mikhail Sergeevich, 1966-1976 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Khitrovo, Vladimir Sergeevich, 1961-1968 and undated (Folder 1: 28)
  - Kiselevskii, Kirill, Vasil'evich, 1970-1975 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Korbe, Nikolai Sergeevich, 1977 and undated (Folder 1: 30)
  - Koval'skii, V., 1969-1977 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Kurcheninov, Valerian Sergeevich, 1975 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Lyons, Marvin, 1973 and undated (Folder 1: 33)
  - Magerovskii, Lev Florianovich, 1975-1978 (Folder 1: 34)
    Includes associated correspondence
  - Maksheev, L. and Maksheeva, A., 1966-1969 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Meshcherinov, Sergei Aleksandrovich, 1969-1970 (Folder 1: 36)
  - Meyendorff, Georgii and Rita, undated (Folder 1: 37)
  - Mikhailov, Mikhail Nikolaevich, 1975 (Folder 1: 38)
  - Mikhalevskii, Sergei, 1971-1978 (Folder 1: 39)
  - Miliutin, G., 1976 (Folder 1: 40)
  - Obruchev, Nikolai Sergeevich, 1976-1977 (Folder 1: 41)
  - Olfer'ev, Fedor Sergeevich, 1966-1968 (Folder 1: 42)
  - Onoshkovich-Iatsyna, Evgenii Nikolaevich, 1969-1970 (Folder 1: 43)
  - Polianskii, A., 1976-1977 (Folder 1: 44)
  - Putiatin, Sergei, undated (Folder 1: 45)
  - Rerberg, Petr F., 1976-1977 (Folder 1: 46)
  - Rogozhin, A., 1947 (Folder 1: 47)
  - Romanenko, A. I., undated (Folder 1: 48)
  - Sannikov, Sergei Aleksandrovich, 1977 (Folder 1: 49)
  - Silin, Vladimir, 1976 and undated (Folder 1: 50)
  - Stenbok-Fermor, Ivan Ivanovich, 1974-1977 (Folder 1: 51)
  - Stolypin, A., undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Timchenko-Ruban, Vladimir Nikolaevich, 1975-1976 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Unkovskii family, 1975 and undated (Folder 2: 3)
  - Val'ter, Valerii Kirillovich, 1966-1977 and undated (Folder 2: 4)
  - Vasil'ev, Rostislav Mstislavovich, 1973-1978 and undated (Folder 2: 5)
  - Velikosel'skii, V., 1974-1975 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Vrangel', Karl, 1975-1976 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Vuich, Nikolai Emmanuilovich, 1975-1976 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Zhadvoin, Nikolai Leonidovich, 1968-1977 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Zhivkovich, Petr, undated (Folder 2: 10)
  - Zubov, Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1970-1977 and undated (Folder 1: 11)
- WRITINGS, 1948-1975
  - "Obshchimi usiliiami - spravilis',"., 1948 January 12 (Folder 2: 12)
    Typescript. Includes related clippings
  - Untitled memoirs (fragments), [1964]
    - Holograph (Folder 2: 13)
    - Typescript (Folder 2: 14)
    - Printed copy ( Sbornik Soiuza pazhei, ), 1964 February (Folder 2: 15)
  - "Vladimir Vasil'evich Semchevskii,"., 1967 November 12 (Folder 2: 16)
    Typescript
  - "Russkaia armiia v romane Solzhenitsyna 'Avgust Chetyrnadtsatogo'," Russkaia zhizn', 1972 March 7 (Folder 2: 17)
    Printed copy. Includes background materials
  - Letter to the editor, Russkaia zhizn', 1975 (Folder 2: 18)
    Printed copy
- SUBJECT FILE, 1917-1978
  - Russia. Armiia
    - General. (Folder 2: 19)
      Includes diary of Gen. Bezobrazov, 1917-1924, and other materials relating to the Konvoi and Konnogvardeiskoe ob"edinenie
    - Corps de Pages. (Folder 2: 20)
      Includes financial records relating to mutual aid of Pages abroad, lists of former pages in emigration, and a typed memoir of the Corps de Pages by P. P. Gudim-Levkovich
    - Leib-gvardii Konno-artilleriiskii polk. (Folder 2: 21)
      Includes lists of members of the regimental association abroad
  - Miscellany (Folder 2: 22)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d. (Folder 2: 23)
  One color reproduction of a painting depicting a Russian military unit, and three prints depicting Semchevskii and friend, a group of officers, and an unidentified interior